<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<parameterSet xmlns="http://msi.umn.edu/tropix/proteomics/parameters/specification" >

<parameter name="enzyme" default="Trypsin">
  <domain>
    <domainElement><value>Trypsin</value></domainElement>
    <domainElement><value>Arg-C</value></domainElement>
    <domainElement><value>Asp-N</value></domainElement>
    <!-- 
    <domainElement><value>Asp-N_ambic</value></domainElement>
     -->
    <domainElement><value>Chymotrypsin</value></domainElement>
    <domainElement><value>CNBr</value></domainElement>
    <!-- <domainElement><value>Formic_acid</value></domainElement>  -->
    <domainElement><value>Lys-C</value></domainElement>
    <domainElement><value>Lys-C/P</value></domainElement>
    <domainElement><value>PepsinA</value></domainElement>
    <!-- 
    <domainElement><value>Tryp-CNBr</value></domainElement>
    <domainElement><value>TrypChymo</value></domainElement>
     -->
    <domainElement><value>V8-DE</value></domainElement>
    <domainElement><value>V8-E</value></domainElement>
    <domainElement><value>No_Enzyme</value></domainElement>
  </domain>
</parameter>

<parameter default="0.0">
  <shortDescription></shortDescription>
  <nameSet>
    <name>fixed[</name>
    <name>fixed]</name>
    <name>fixedG</name>
    <name>fixedS</name>
    <name>fixedP</name>
    <name>fixedV</name>
    <name>fixedT</name>
    <name>fixedC</name>
    <name>fixedL</name>
    <name>fixedI</name>
    <name>fixedX</name>
    <name>fixedN</name>
    <name>fixedO</name>
    <name>fixedB</name>
    <name>fixedD</name>
    <name>fixedQ</name>
    <name>fixedK</name>
    <name>fixedZ</name>
    <name>fixedE</name>
    <name>fixedM</name>
    <name>fixedH</name>
    <name>fixedF</name>
    <name>fixedR</name>
    <name>fixedY</name>
    <name>fixedW</name>
    <name>fixedA</name>

    <name>potential[</name>
    <name>potential]</name>
    <name>potentialG</name>
    <name>potentialS</name>
    <name>potentialP</name>
    <name>potentialV</name>
    <name>potentialT</name>
    <name>potentialC</name>
    <name>potentialL</name>
    <name>potentialI</name>
    <name>potentialX</name>
    <name>potentialN</name>
    <name>potentialO</name>
    <name>potentialB</name>
    <name>potentialD</name>
    <name>potentialQ</name>
    <name>potentialK</name>
    <name>potentialZ</name>
    <name>potentialE</name>
    <name>potentialM</name>
    <name>potentialH</name>
    <name>potentialF</name>
    <name>potentialR</name>
    <name>potentialY</name>
    <name>potentialW</name>
    <name>potentialA</name>
    
    <name>refinePotMod[</name>
    <name>refinePotMod]</name>
    <name>refinePotModG</name>
    <name>refinePotModS</name>
    <name>refinePotModP</name>
    <name>refinePotModV</name>
    <name>refinePotModT</name>
    <name>refinePotModC</name>
    <name>refinePotModL</name>
    <name>refinePotModI</name>
    <name>refinePotModX</name>
    <name>refinePotModN</name>
    <name>refinePotModO</name>
    <name>refinePotModB</name>
    <name>refinePotModD</name>
    <name>refinePotModQ</name>
    <name>refinePotModK</name>
    <name>refinePotModZ</name>
    <name>refinePotModE</name>
    <name>refinePotModM</name>
    <name>refinePotModH</name>
    <name>refinePotModF</name>
    <name>refinePotModR</name>
    <name>refinePotModY</name>
    <name>refinePotModW</name>
    <name>refinePotModA</name>
    
  </nameSet>
  <validation type="float" />
</parameter>


<parameter name="outputHistogramColumnWidth" default="50">
<shortDescription></shortDescription>
<longDescription>
This parameter sets the number of values in a GAML-type histogram that
are listed on a single line of output. It can be used to limit the
length of lines in the output file, although it has no effect on true
XML parsers.
</longDescription>
<validation type="int" minValue="0" />
</parameter>


<parameter name="outputHistograms" default="true">
<shortDescription></shortDescription>
<longDescription>When this value is set to yes, the histograms
containing the statistical information about an spectrum-to-sequence
assignment are written to the output file. If it is set to no, then
these histograms are not recorded.</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>


<parameter name="outputMaximumValidExpectationValue" default="1000.0">
<shortDescription></shortDescription>
<longDescription>When the output, results value is set to valid, the
value of this parameter sets the maximum expectation value recorded in
the output file for a modelling session. All results with expectation
values less than this value are considered to be statisitically
significant and are recorded. In the case that output, results value
is set to stochastic, results with expectation values greater than
this value are recorded.</longDescription>
<validation type="float" minValue="0.0" />
</parameter>



<parameter name="outputOneSequencePerCopy" default="false">
<shortDescription></shortDescription>
<longDescription>Protein sequences are normally stored in the X!
Tandem output file format, represented in BIOML. If multiple peptides
from a single protein sequence are found, then that protein sequence
is by default reported for each peptide. If this parameter is set to
yes, then the full protein sequence is only recorded for the first
peptide in a file corresponding to that protein. Subsequent peptides
only have the protein's unique identifier (UID) recorded. This UID is
assigned by X! Tandem, based on the ordinal position of the protein in
a sequence file. For example, if a protein was the 123rd protein read
from a file during a search, then that protein's UID would be
123.</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="outputPerformance" default="true">
<shortDescription>When this value is set to yes, all of the modelling session performance parameters supplied by X! TANDEM are written into the XML output file.</shortDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="outputProteins" default="true">
<shortDescription></shortDescription>
<longDescription>When this value is set to yes, the BIOML protein
information associated with a peptide-to-spectrum match are recorded
in the XML output file. This is the recommended mode of operation for
X! TANDEM, as it records the version of the protein sequence actually
used for the identification. Sequence lists generated from database
systems can change from time-to-time, with the deletion of accession
numbers and the alteration of protein sequences associated with a
particular accession number. If the output, sequences value is no,
then all of the information in the protein node is written, except
for the full sequence of the protein.

If it is set to no, then the protein nodes are not recorded. The
recording of the input parameters,performance statistics or other
types of results are not affected by the value of this
parameter.</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="outputResults" default="all">
<shortDescription></shortDescription>
<longDescription>
The value for this parameter determines which results are written to
the output file at the end of a modelling session. The three possible
values cover the most interesting use cases for X! TANDEM, from a
bioinformatics perspective. The exact form of the reported results
will depend on the values chosen for other output parameters.

1. all - When this value is set, results are reported for all of the
spectra that were used in the modelling session. This value is not
recommended for normal use, as most spectra in a large data set will
not return useful results. Storing the large volume of purely
stochastic matches that can results is a waste of resources, for most
users.  2. valid - When this value is set, results that have an
expectation value less than output, maximum valid expectation value
are reported. This setting is of the most general use.  3. stochastic
- When this value is set, results that have an expectation value
greater than output, maximum valid expectation value are all
reported. This is the compliment to the valid set, and it can be
useful for debugging and bioinformatics purposes.
</longDescription>
<domain>
<domainElement><value>valid</value></domainElement>
<domainElement><value>stocastic</value></domainElement>
<domainElement><value>all</value></domainElement>
</domain>
<validation />
</parameter>

<parameter name="outputSortResultsBy" default="protein">
<shortDescription></shortDescription>
<longDescription>
When this value is set to spectrum, the output file contains the
results of a modelling session in the same order as the spectra were
recorded in the original spectra file. Each result group is numbered
with the ordinal position of the spectrum, or the spectrum number
obtained from the original file (if available).

When this value is set to protein, the output file contains the
results of a modelling session listed according to a particular
spectrum's corresponding peptide's position in the most likely protein
sequence, starting at the N-terminus of the protein. All of the
peptides associated with a particular protein are list
sequentially. The most likely protein in the data set is listed first,
with others listed in order of descending confidence of assignment.
</longDescription>
<domain>
<domainElement><value>protein</value></domainElement>
<domainElement><value>spectrum</value></domainElement>
</domain>
</parameter>

<parameter name="outputSequences" default="true">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
When this value is set to yes, the protein sequences associated with a
peptide-to-spectrum match are recorded in the XML output file. This is
the recommended mode of operation for X! TANDEM, as it records the
version of the protein sequence actually used for the
identification. Sequence lists generated from database systems can
change from time-to-time, with the deletion of accession numbers and
the alteration of protein sequences associated with a particular
accession number. If the output, proteins value is no, then this
parameter is ignored.

If it is set to no, then these sequences are not recorded. The
recording of the input parameters,performance statistics or other
types of results are not affected by the value of this parameter.
</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="outputSpectra" default="true">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
When this value is set to yes, the spectra used in the modelling
session, are recorded in GAML format in the output XML file. When
these spectra have been recorded in an output file, the output file
can be used as an input spectrum source file for further analysis with
X! TANDEM.

If it is set to no, then these spectra are not recorded. The recording
of the input parameters,performance statistics or other types of
results are not affected by the value of this parameter.
</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="proteinCleavageCTerminalMassChange" default="0.0">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
This value represents the mass added to the C-terminus of a peptide
after undergoing peptide bond cleavage by a chemical or enzymatic
reagent, in Daltons. The default value is the mass change associated
with hydrolytic cleavage in normal water.
</longDescription>
<validation type="float" /> <!-- pos or neg values allowed -->
</parameter>

<parameter name="proteinCleavageNTerminalMassChange" default="0.0">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
This value represents the mass added to the N-terminus of a peptide
after undergoing peptide bond cleavage by a chemical or enzymatic
reagent, in Daltons. The default value is the mass change associated
with hydrolytic cleavage in normal water.
</longDescription>
<validation type="float" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="proteinCleavageSemi" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
In real experiments, there are often contaminating proteolytic enzymes
which will act on proteins in a difficult to predict
manner. Therefore, the idea of a semi-tryptic digest was developed
to attempt to compensate for this additional cleavage activity. This
cleavage type assumes that one of the cleavage sites is tryptic
([KR]|{P}), but the other site may be at any residue. For example, if
an expected tryptic peptide has a sequence of TFGQVVAR, then the
semi-tryptic peptides associated with this sequence would be:

TFGQVVAR
 FGQVVAR
  GQVVAR
   QVVAR
    VVAR
     VAR
      AR
TFGQVVA
TFGQVV
TFGQV
TFGQ
TFG
TF

Tandem has broadened this concept to include any cleavage site
specification, except for cleavage at any site ([X]|[X]), which
doesn't require any additional type of cleavage.
</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="proteinCleavageSite" default="[KR]|{P}">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/pcs.html
</longDescription>
<!-- Need regex for this -->
<validation type="string" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="proteinCTerminalResidueModificationMass" default="0.0">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
This value represents any additional fixed modification mass added
only to the C-terminal residue in an intact protein, in Daltons.
</longDescription>
<validation type="float" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="proteinNTerminalResidueModificationMass" default="0.0">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
This value represents any additional fixed modification mass added
only to the N-terminal residue in an intact protein, in Daltons.
</longDescription>
<validation type="float" />
</parameter>


<parameter name="residueModificationMass" default="">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/rmm.html</longDescription>
<validation type="string" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="residuePotentialModificationMass" default="">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/rpmm.html</longDescription>
<validation type="string" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="residuePotentialModificationMotif" default="">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/rpmmotif.html</longDescription>
<validation type="string" />
</parameter>


<parameter name="scoringAIons" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>If the value is yes, then peptide sequence a ions are used in the spectrum scoring algorithm.</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="scoringBIons" default="true">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>If the value is yes, then peptide sequence b ions are used in the spectrum scoring algorithm.</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="scoringCIons" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>If the value is yes, then peptide sequence c ions are used in the spectrum scoring algorithm.</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="scoringXIons" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>If the value is yes, then peptide sequence x ions are used in the spectrum scoring algorithm.</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="scoringYIons" default="true">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>If the value is yes, then peptide sequence y ions are used in the spectrum scoring algorithm.</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="scoringZIons" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>If the value is yes, then peptide sequence z ions are used in the spectrum scoring algorithm.</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>


<parameter name="scoringCyclicPermutation" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
X! Tandem performs a detailed statistical analysis on the peptides
found during a search to determine which results are statistically
valid. This analysis depends on comparing the best result of a search
to the distribution of all other peptide sequences that matched the
parent ion mass tolerance test. While it only takes approximately 300
peptides to generate a reliable distribution, if a very small sequence
collection is used, there may be too few matching peptides to generate
a reliable distribution. If the distribution is too small, default
values are used to calculate the expectation value for a result.

While the default values are reasonable, they may lead to over or
under estimation of the true expectation value. To try to generate a
distribution for very small sequence collections, setting this
parameter to yes generates a set of cyclic permutations of each
peptide that falls within the parent ion tolerance. This set of
peptides, given the sequence YGGFLR would be:

   1. YGGFLR - the initial sequence
   2. RYGGFL
   3. LRYGGF
   4. FLRYGG
   5. GFLRYG
   6. GGFLRY
   7. RLFGGY
   8. YRLFGG
   9. GYRLFG
  10. GGYRLF
  11. FGGYRL
  12. LFGGYR

Each of these alternative sequences is scored and used to construct
the scoring distribution, but they are not stored in the output, even
if they have better scores than the initial peptide sequence.
</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="scoringIncludeReverse" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
Due to the structure of some older search engines, no statistical
information is compiled about the validity of the results. As an
after-the-fact kluge to correct this problem, it has become common
practice to repeat a search using the same set of protein sequences,
with the protein sequences altered to be written in reverse order (a
so-called "reverse database search"). By comparing the scores produced
by this "reverse" search and the normal search, it is possible to very
crudely estimate whether a result is potentially a false positive.

The statistical analysis done by X! Tandem makes this type of crude
estimate unnecessary. However, to make comparisons possible, X! Tandem
has a protein sequence reverse method built in. When the value of this
parameter is yes, the protein sequences are first searched normally
and then reversed in memory and searched again. The tag ":reversed" is
added to the protein description, so that peptides corresponding to
reversed sequences can be distinguished in the output. Using this
feature regularly is not recommended, as it doubles the time required
to perform a search and the use of reversed searches for validation
has no general statistical value.
</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="scoringMaximumMissedCleavageSites" default="1">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
When a cleavage reagent (either chemical or enzymatic) is used to
cleave the peptide backbone of a protein to produce peptides,
different sites along the backbone will have different reaction rates
and kinetics. Therefore, there may be some sites that should be
cleaved by the reagent that are not completely cleaved during the
course of the experiment. The value of this parameter represents the
maximum number of missed cleavage sites allowed within a peptide. For
a specific, aggressive enzyme such as trypsin, the number of missed
sites will be low: a value of 1 or 2 is appropriate. For a
non-specific enzyme, such as pepsin, then a value of 50 is more
appropriate.

The value chosen for this parameter affects the overall speed of the
calculation. The number of peptides considered for a particular
protein sequence is linearly proportional to the parameter value, so
the amount of time necessary for the calculation will vary roughly
linearly with the value chosen. In practice, TANDEM performs somewhat
better than linear when doing this type of calculation.
</longDescription>
<validation type="integer" minValue="0" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="scoringMinimumIonCount" default="0">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
Practically, there is some minimum number of assignable
sequence-specific ions in a spectrum that is necessary to consider the
spectrum as a match to a peptide sequence. The value of this parameter
sets the minumum number of total ions that must be assigned for a
score to be calculated and stored in the scoring histogram structure
used by TANDEM to track the statistical nature of the stochastic
distribution.
</longDescription>
<validation type="integer" minValue="0" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumContrastAngle" default="0.0">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/sca.html</longDescription>
<validation type="float" minValue="0.0" maxValue="90.0" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumDynamicRange" default="1000.0">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
This parameter is used to normalize the intensity values of fragment
ions, from spectrum to spectrum. For example, if Drange = 100.0, then
the intensity of the most intense peak in a spectrum is set to 100,
and all of the other intensities are linearly scaled to that
intensity. Any peak with a scaled intensity of less than 1 is rejected
as being outside of the dynamic range. Therefore, in addition to
normalizing the spectra, it sets an effective relative threshold for
peaks.
</longDescription>
<validation type="float" minValue="1.0000001"  />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumFragmentMassError" default="0.0">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/sfme.html</longDescription>
<validation type="float" minValue="0.0" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumFragmentMassErrorUnits" default="Daltons">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
</longDescription>
<domain><domainElement><value>Daltons</value></domainElement><domainElement><value>ppm</value></domainElement></domain>
<validation />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumFragmentMassType" default="monoisotopic">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
Naturally occuring organic molecules do not have a single value
corresponding to the mass of the molecule. Because organic molecules
contain carbon, any collection of molecules will have some probability
of containing one or more 13C atoms. In mass spectrometry, it is
common to refer to the weighted average of all possible 13C-containing
molecular masses as the chemical or average mass of the
molecule. When this parameter is set to average, this weighted average
is used to calculate the masses of the fragment ions in a tandem mass
spectrum.

Most modern mass spectrometers have sufficient mass resolution so that
the mass of each of the individual 13C-containing species can be
measured separately. The lowest mass of these peaks will contain only
12C atoms. This lowest mass peak in the isotopic distribution measured
is commonly refered to as the monoisotopic mass for the molecule
(also refered to as the A0 peak). When this parameter is set to
monoisotopic, this peak is used to define the mass of the fragment
ions.
</longDescription>
<domain><domainElement><value>monoisotopic</value></domainElement><domainElement><value>average</value></domainElement></domain>
<validation />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumMinimumFragmentMZ" default="0.0">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
The fragment ion mass spectra produced by peptides contain peaks that
are sequence-specific and those that are caused by individual amino
acid residues. The peaks caused by these individual amino acid
residues tend to be relatively small (m/z &lt; 200) and they do not
affect the outcome of a search. However, these peaks can be very
intense, sometimes dwarfing the sequence-specific peaks used by TANDEM
to discover appropriate model peptide sequences. The value of Mfmin is
used to remove these intense (but not very useful) peaks, prior to
normalization. Any peak that does not meet the condition:

m/z > Mfmin

is rejected. 
</longDescription>
<validation type="float" minValue="0.0" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumMinimumPeaks" default="0">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
The MS/MS spectra used in peptide sequence searches are composed of a
limited number of mass-to-charge ratio:intensity pairs. Many common
types of mass spectrometer data systems will generate a mass spectrum
during a chromatographic run, even if the parent ion does not
fragment. The value of this parameter is used to screen out spectra
that contain too few fragment ions to be usefully interpreted.

If the total number of mass-to-charge ratio:intensity pairs is a
particular spectrum is N, then the condition that a spectrum is
considered to have too few ions to be considered would be:

N &lt; Nmin
</longDescription>
<validation type="int" minValue="0" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumMinimumParentMH" default="0.0">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
This parameter is used to supress the analysis of spectra that were
generated by low mass parent ions. Depending on the instrumentation
and excitation energy used to generate fragment ions, there will be
some low mass cutoff value, below which there is very little chance of
generating an interpretable MS/MS spectrum. In many experimental
conditions, there will also be noise peaks in the parent ion spectrum,
generated by the ion source and chemical noise. The value selected for
Mmin is used to reject these spectra.
</longDescription>
<validation type="float" minValue="0.0000001" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumNeutralLossMass" default="466.0">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
The value of this parameter is ignored if spectrum, use neutral loss window = yes.

Some types of post-translational or chemical modifications can produce
intense peaks in a spectrum because of a favoured fragmentation
mechanism produced by the loss of a stable neutral molecule. These
neutral loss peaks can be removed from a spectrum by setting
appropriate values for the spectrum, neutral loss window, Wnl and Mnl
parameters.

If the spectrum, use neutral loss window value is yes, then any peaks
with an m/z value that meets the following condition is rejected:

| m/z - Mnl | &lt; Wnl

Any peak that has been removed using this mechanism is reinserted into
the spectrum before the spectrum is written to the output XML data
file, even though it was not considered during the peptide modelling
process.
</longDescription>
<validation type="float" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumNeutralLossWindow" default="15.0">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
Some types of post-translational or chemical modifications can produce
intense peaks in a spectrum because of a favoured fragmentation
mechanism produced by the loss of a stable neutral molecule. These
neutral loss peaks can be removed from a spectrum by setting
appropriate values for the Wnl and spectrum, neutral loss mass, Mnl
parameters.

If the spectrum, use neutral loss window value is yes, then any peaks
with an m/z value that meets the following condition is rejected:

| m/z - Mnl | &lt; Wnl

Any peak that has been removed using this mechanism is reinserted into
the spectrum before the spectrum is written to the output XML data
file, even though it was not considered during the peptide modelling
process.
</longDescription>
<validation type="float" minValue="0.000000000001" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumParentMonoisotopicMassErrorMinus" default="0.0">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/spmmem.html
</longDescription>
<validation type="float" minValue="0.0" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumParentMonoisotopicMassErrorPlus" default="0.0">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/spmmep.html
</longDescription>
<validation type="float" minValue="0.0" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumParentMonoisotopicMassErrorUnits" default="Daltons">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/spmmeu.html
</longDescription>
<domain>
  <domainElement><value>Daltons</value></domainElement>
  <domainElement><value>ppm</value></domainElement>
</domain>
<validation />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumParentMonoisotopicMassIsotopeError" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
When the value for this parameter is yes, the parent ion mass
tolerance is expanded by opening up multiple tolerance windows
centered on the first and second 13C isotope peaks for a peptide. This
behavior is necessary to compensate for the tendency of automated peak
finding software to return the most intense peak from a cluster of
isotopes, rather than the all-12C peak. It should only be used if the
parent ion mass error parameters are set so that the error will be &lt;
0.5 Da.
</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumTotalPeaks" default="50">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/stp.html
</longDescription>
<validation type="integer" minValue="1" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumUseNeutralLossWindow" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
Some types of post-translational or chemical modifications can produce
intense peaks in a spectrum because of a favoured fragmentation
mechanism produced by the loss of a stable neutral molecule. These
neutral loss peaks can be removed from a spectrum by setting
appropriate values for the spectrum, neutral loss window and spectrum,
neutral loss mass parameters.
</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumUseNoiseSuppression" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
X! TANDEM uses several mechanisms to attempt to reduce the number of
spectra considered in a list of spectra. When this parameter is set to
yes, spectra that fit the pattern of noise - spectra caused by the
fragmentation of chemical noise peaks - are rejected without further
analysis. This feature can be very useful when dealling with large
amounts of data from automated LC/MS experiments. Some experimentation
may be required to determine what settings are appropriate for the
noise detection filters (see the links below). Setting the parameter
to no skips the noise filters and allows all spectra to be modelled.
</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>


<parameter name="spectrumUseContrastAngle" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>When this value is set to yes, contrast angle
filtering is used to remove similar mass spectra from a spectrum list.
</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="spectrumMaximumParentCharge" default="10">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>
</longDescription>
<validation type="integer" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="refine" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/refine.html
</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="refineCleavageSemi" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/rcsemi.html
</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="refineMaximumValidExpectationValue" default="1000.0"> <!--  High value used for scaffold -->
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/refmvev.html
</longDescription>
</parameter>

<parameter name="refineModificationMass" default="">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/refmm.html
</longDescription>
</parameter>

<parameter name="refinePointMutations" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/rpm.html
</longDescription>
</parameter>

<parameter name="refinePotentialModificationMass" default="">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/refpmm.html
</longDescription>
</parameter>

<parameter name="refinePotentialModificationMotif" default="">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/refpmmotif.html
</longDescription>
</parameter>

<parameter name="refineSingleAminoAcidPolymorphisms" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/rsaps.html
</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="refineSpectrumSynthesis" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/rss.html
</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="refineUnanticipatedCleavage" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/ruc.html
</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="refineUsePotentialModifications" default="false">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription>http://www.thegpm.org/TANDEM/api/rupmffr.html
</longDescription>
<validation type="boolean" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="refinePotentialNTerminusModifications" default="0.0">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription></longDescription>
<validation type="float" />
</parameter>

<parameter name="refinePotentialCTerminusModifications" default="0.0">
<shortDescription>
</shortDescription>
<longDescription></longDescription>
<validation type="float" />
</parameter>


</parameterSet>
